[Music]
this is software engineering radio, the podcast for professional developers on the web at se-radio.net.
sc radio is brought to you by the ieee computer society by ieee software magazine online at computer.org software.
hello everyone this is priyanka raghavan for software engineering radio.
today we'll be discussing the osp top 10 with our guest vandana varma.
vandala is the vice chairperson owasp global board of directors.
and she also has experience ranging from application security to infrastructure security vulnerability management cloud security and now dealing with product security.
she currently works at sync.
she has various initiatives that she contributes to which includes diversity in initiatives like infosec girls and warsec.
she's also been a key influencer in these spears.
but apart from that she's a regular talk show post kind of a thing if the os spotlight.
she's also been at various conferences such as black hat and the wasp meetups.
it's great to have a conversation with you now.
we're really looking forward to the show.
welcome thank you so much and i'm really really glad to be part of the show.
priyanka vantana we've at software engineering radio we've done quite a lot of shows with respect to you know application security.
in terms of secure coding practices for software engineers.
we've also done api security network security.
we've also done a show on xero trust networks.
but we've never really done a show on the osp top 10 which is like the mantra for most software teams.
so that's why we decided to do this show and of course you're the right guest for this.
before we start off would you be able to give us a definition or a way to explain what is wasp to our listeners.
absolutely so ovasp is ow asp it's one of those communities which is spread across the world.
and to precisely say it's more around application security.
it's a non-profit organization trying to bring forward application security.
and work towards to improve the security of the softwares through community-led open source software projects hundreds of local chapters worldwide.
and many people getting involved in it.
i personally get involved in a lot of things at ovas.
so it's one of those places where you can learn a lot.
if you don't know anything about application security this is the place to go.
just go to project section you can check out many projects from os a web testing guide to whatnot and you find everything there.
if you want to connect with like-minded people who are talking about application security or network security or even kubernetes containers this is the community for you.
you can look at the chapter near you.
so probably it's a place where you feel warm connected. that's in a nutshell of us.
great i think i can personally vouch for that.
i think that's one of the places where i also met security enthusiasts at the local bangalore meetup.
the other thing i want to ask you is wasp top 10 how did this idea come about.
to you know list the top 10 most common areas that one should focus on. how did that come up.
right so when we talk about application security it was booming up at that time.
we were getting a lot of bugs even there was a cross-site scripting which was reported in microsoft as well.
so that's how xs has came into picture.
it didn't become css because style sheets was already there.
but then there were efforts which were needed by the people for the people and for the community.
and that's how some people gathered together and came up with something called as owasp top ten.
which is open web application security project top 10 which are top 10 risks in the web applications.
and they keep changing every few years.
and that's how the idea came in where and those people said oh we need something which industry can actually look forward to.
if i understand something in certain way you might understand in a certain other way as well because we have different perception of things.
that's why people said we need to have single perception of the top 10 risks.
and those top 10 risks are not just top 10 but there are underlying vulnerabilities associated with them underlying risk associated with that.
so that's how it culminated.
okay great and also one of the things i noticed is that the wasp top 10 seems to be getting updated like once in four years.
i don't know because there is 20 21 and before that there was a 2017 i think before that was 2013.
so is the frequency once in four years or do you aim for something quicker.
i feel that it was supposed to be three years and due to unforeseen circumstances the frequency gets delayed sometimes.
so the top 10 for 2020 was supposed to be released in 2020 but they mentioned in 2021 because of covet because.
of people not getting the data.
so this top 10 list is not just like you and i wrote it or the leaders wrote it.
no there's a data that get gathered from a lot of places from companies from the vendors from everyone.
and then that gets processed by machine learning and that's how the top 10 comes into picture.
and even that's even being shared with the community to vote.
that process is a very exhaustive process.
that's why in 2020 we could not gather the data ample of data to come up with the right list.
and that's how it came in september 2021 when ovas celebrated 20th anniversary.
oh interesting very interesting.
in fact i was going to ask you what are the sources of the data and you just answered that.
i am also curious like how does that do you give a survey out to all the companies.
and then they fill that up and say what are they seeing.
or does it come from like their pen test reports or any of the tools that they're running with their source code analysis things like that.
actually it's a mix of it it's not just the pen test reports i agree it's like a pen test report.
it's the survey it's the kind of bug organization see the list of bugs that organizations see.
so ovas leaders have collaboration with many many organizations and vendors.
and then we pick up the list of most renowned bugs or most seen bugs that are impacting the organizations worldwide.
not just in one place not just in u.s not just in uk not just in india but everywhere. and that's how it comes up.
and this data is a mix of a lot of things in checking how much risk vulnerability is pausing and what sector it's pausing all of those things.
that's very interesting.
i in fact wanted to ask you one thing in terms of the data.
do you look at say how frequently a vulnerability comes up on the application.
or is it like the likelihood of that vulnerability occurring.
you know it's possible to get into some little detail before we jump into the wasp top ten.
so frequency of occurring is actually it's subjected because this one i specifically saw in detail.
there were many cwes which is common weakness enumeration that are part of each vulnerability.
if you go and check out at ova's top 10 page with every vulnerability there are many cwes associated with it.
so when the data is scrubbed it's checked that what is the frequency of it how exactly differentiated from others.
for example i'll give you an example and then it will be explained better.
like authentication controls broken authentication control has gone to top list.
so in broken authentication control itself there are 34 cwes mapped.
so each one has a different area could be violation of privilege escalation or violation of principles of least privilege.
maybe when you are not supposed to edit something and you are having that access certain issues around apis.
so it underlies multiple aspects of each bug or different use cases.
that's very interesting and i i didn't know there was that kind of detail which goes in.
maybe that's further reading and i'll add that in our show notes so people can take a look at the oauth page as well.
i guess now we can move into the top 10 vulnerabilities for 2021.
and so i'll just maybe read out each element and we'll go through that and sort of get your view on it.
maybe a definition or some example whatever you think from your point of view makes sense for people to look out for.
so i think the first one on the 2021 list is the broken access control.
and if i look at the stats from wasp it says that 94 of the applications from the survey and the data had some form of broken access control.
so could you kind of explain the importance of this broken access control and what exactly is it.
absolutely when we talk about this bug it was moved from fifth position to first position.
the basic reason was that when the data was gathered they realized that most of the issues that are arising.
they are arising because we are exposing certain sensitive data which should not be shared.
and that happens because of access controls that we don't have the right set of access controls.
for example right now you are the podcast host priyanka i am a podcast guest.
and if i am getting access to the podcast all the recordings have passed that means the privileges are not properly set.
so when that came into picture we realized that every vulnerability that has some connection to broken access control some or the other way.
and on top of it if you see this over top 10 that goes in very much in sync.
okay this is not there oh this could be a problem this is not there this is the problem.
so it goes very much in tandem.
and this vulnerability specifically says that let's take care of access let's get the right access at the right time to the right person for the right role.
because if we don't do that we would see the problems coming on.
and it does not stop there it also comes along with another aspect that metadata manipulation we've seen with ssrf.
which is a top 10 list and the 10th one now.
that also links again with a broken access control that we don't have the right access and that's why somebody was able to manipulate it.
so that's why they've marked it as top one.
and as you mentioned rightly the 94 percent of the applications were tested for some of the other broken access controls.
wow and interestingly it all ties to the items in the list as well as you just brought out.
okay i think that's a pretty good overview of broken access control.
so let's move on to the next one which is the cryptographic failures.
i think this was previously called sensitive data exposure it's on the list.
do you think it's because of all the hacks we've been reading online for the past couple of years.
there's been so much of leakage of sensitive data and cryptographic failures contribute to that.
absolutely they do contribute.
and when we talk about sensitive data exposure uh think of hard-coded passwords in your code that has been like one turning and twisting point.
on top of it a lot of applications still have certain ports open where data can be fetched.
or think of you and i are using some channel of communication which is on http.
and this does not stop there you would see a lot of places wherein there are certain bank pages.
think of it as bank pages which are only supposed to be accessed when you're logged in.
and now when you're not logged in i can open it in some other browser how cool that would be for a attacker.
amazing now server side certificates have become a trend but if you start using self-signed certificates will there be a problem.
absolutely it will be a big problem.
if you're using a depreciated or deprecated algorithm like md5 hash or sha one hash which are easy to break.
now for me it will be amazing but for you it will be problematic.
so it's very very important to understand like how much they contribute to these things and how much they can be helpful.
and on top of it now we have started using keys a lot.
if keys are not being stored properly or if the keys are not managed properly what will we do.
there's nothing that we can do and who to blame for only ourselves.
these things become so common.
you know you're just speaking to someone who spent about a week now trying to find out bunch of these issues like where do you store the keys properly.
finding that credentials have been there in github on maybe not in the right area with the right amount of privileges anybody could see.
so yeah it's been quite stressful at work because i think the original thing is trying to first take care of things.
and do it properly the first time then yeah.
so i think i should be sort of having this list printed onto my desktop as well.
i think i'll go to the next one one now which is the injection attacks they are number three on the list.
from the survey it says that again this is something like 95 percent have said that they've had one form of injection or the other.
and for me when i think of injection i only think of you know sequel injections.
but you as an expert can probably break it down for us a little bit on what are the different types of injections.
i would say that this is one of my favorite an all-time favorite.
i'll tell you the reason for it because when you look at oas top 10 injection has always been on the top.
and when it's on the top and it's coming down to third level it brings us to a point that it is going away no.
why because xss has also been clubbed with it now.
and on top of it if i say this that like when we were kids these vulnerabilities was there but this vulnerability specifically was there.
we've grown up our kids are going to grow up and this is going to be there why.
as soon as the list came out i saw log fishing then many many remote code executions came into picture.
so these vulnerabilities are not gonna go away you would keep seeing these injections to what not. that's funny but that's the truth.
yeah i think that's brilliantly brought out by the log4j example that you gave here.
so it just brought us right back into thinking about how we do logging and thinking about who might use our logging frameworks here.
the next one on the list the fourth item which is insecure design actually caught me a bit by surprise.
that's great because i think one of the things is everybody keeps talking about shifting left.
is this to encourage developers and teams to start doing more threat analysis or threat modeling.
you're right some way yes but insecurities design talks about even the more that let's go ahead and understand security better from the start.
there's a principle called secure by design so it talks about that and also impresses on moving just beyond shift left.
understanding where it all starts when even the discussion starts so this actually talks about that.
this is one of the most interesting ones because we have never seen it like overasp can talk about insecure design.
but if you don't have the right design you would always have these vulnerabilities.
and vulnerabilities we would never be able to fix it if we are not able to architect our design.
now we are moving to cloud right we have so many instances i think everything is moving to cloud.
when that's happening it is important to architect it securely from the design itself from the very get go.
so that when we host things we are not doubtful oh how the things were going to be where exactly is what and we know it end to end.
i think that's what makes it more helpful.
at the same time it emphasizes on the concept of let's design it right.
it also talks about culture methodology and whatnot.
and i think somewhere i had heard that security vulnerabilities exists in application and software because of bad design.
so because you've not really thought about how to build the system which is why people are able to exploit it.
right like right from right buffer of overflows too.
yeah that's interesting.
what's your take on threat modeling we had done a you know separate episode on threat modeling.
but for application teams what do you think about you know significance of say getting developers into this exercise.
can i get a take on that from you.
when we talk about threat modeling it's one of those things which should be done on our applications or even network.
why just applications and even you can do the threat modeling in the code wherein you understand where exactly flaws can understand.
and that's why we all do it.
so if you want to know more about it instead of me saying you should also look at threat modeling manifesto.
so that's by the leaders of owasp they have created this manifesto.
and it's a beautiful place to look at different aspects of threat modeling.
they cover everything end-to-end why you should do how it can be done why is it important and what are the aspects to look at in a wider area.
i'll be sure to add that to the show notes threat modeling manifesto.
in fact i i'm not sure if this was quoted in the previous episode but i'll definitely add this to the reading list.
the next set of items which i want to look at is i think to do with security misconfigurations and outdated libraries etc.
so let me go to the the next item which is the fifth item in the list which talks about security misconfiguration.
i think just now it's spoken about you know everything going on to the cloud.
so maybe do you have some interesting examples from either what you've read or right what you've researched on.
yeah i'll tell you funny story it's actually not funny for someone it can be scary as well.
so this happened when i was working for a client and it's not a recent incident.
so what happened we were testing the whole network and applications both because we were supposed to scan it was more of a pen testing activity.
now when we were scanning the ecosystem we saw certain accounts and the scan came up as default passwords.
like who keep the default passwords all right it should not be right if it's a server it should not be.
then we started checking the ip and we started accessing those ips via browser.
it came up with a camera vendor and it was asking for a username and password.
it took just few seconds for us to get to the password because as soon as you search internet it's easy to find the default passwords for any vendor.
we look through the fourth password i remember fourth or fourth or fifth year if i'm not wrong and we were able to access the camera.
it was just right across the cafeteria and there were many other ips that were there as listed so we tried checking each one of them.
now the funny part is that if you if you're working on something critical or if you're part of the legal team.
and i have access to the camera what more i can do.
think of it there's an external person who has come inside the organization.
and that person has access to the the whole network and then they are able to access the cameras what more i can do.
if someone is a disgruntled employee what will you do they'll have access to anything and everything that you're doing all the paperwork.
it looks nice for me to exploit that bug but that it is not nice for an organization to have that bug.
so that's what this particular vulnerability talk about is security misconfiguration.
why do we keep passwords and i have a simple analogy.
so priyanka do you use toothbrush every day.
yes yes. do you share with anyone.
neither never.
so passwords are like toothbrushes they are your personal hygiene.
why do you share it with your parents with your partner with your friends and friends friends and whatnot.
why do we have to do that let's not do it let's keep our password secure like our toothbrushes.
and on top of it a lot of times what developers do it they keep distract traces open which give us a lot of information.
or they leave the banner disclosure open or there are certain features which are not supposed to be open and they're still open.
so they have to be very much secure right.
specifically i think with application teams what we see is that when you're accessing resources on the cloud.
and then the credentials to access those resources you want to share it with your team member.
and you rather just do it by you know sharing it on a popular chat window or you know chat application.
and then so you just the work gets done and they don't want to nobody wants to take that extra step.
of going to a key vault and picking out those values.
so and that can lead to your disastrous consequences.
but the one with the example that you gave with the cameras is yeah it's quite scary.
the other one i want to talk about which is the next item in the list is the vulnerable and outdated components.
a lot of us in this show and also within many organizations i think we spent the last few weeks of december working on the log 4j vulnerability remediation.
generally i think a lot of people couldn't take the christmas new year time off because they were fixing their apps.
in this scenario how important is this vulnerable and outdated components.
is it should it be six on the list or do you think it's going to be like moved up for the future.
it should be moved up it has moved up from ninth to sixth.
i'll tell you you just mentioned lock for j you remember equifax breach which happened.
yes yes now when you remember that that signifies that yes these kind of bugs should be fixed.
or what will happen we will keep remembering these breaches and for ages and or the years to come.
we don't want that we want something which we can actually forget or we don't want the breaches at all.
breaches are inevitable they will happen but the one thing to remember is how we can fix it how we can come back from it.
so there are certain aspects to it is that why do you want it to happen in the first place right.
so it becomes even the more important let's keep our things up to date or you will see yourself getting reached.
nobody would be responsible for it everyone will blame you for it.
idly there's no one to blame for but then when a breach happens organization is getting targeted like anything.
think of solarwinds attack right so what happened with that the whole supply chain thing.
when i have to give an example about supply chain issues or attacks this particular case comes into my mind.
why because it becomes so important so huge that everybody was like oh we need to do it we need to do it.
even the local news channel started talking about it that was that much insane.
so it's important that let's work towards making sure that we keep our systems designed right up to date.
i think it's yeah pretty interesting because with these outdated components.
yeah sometimes i do see even you know a repos or something that i work with.
it's always convenient to you know work on something that's very popular which might have vulnerabilities.
but you just you just want things to work and so you just take it up and do it because that's the way we work nowadays.
i mean development is a lot faster with third-party off-the-shelf components.
but then there is you know this balance that you you really need to make sure that you keep updating.
because the more number of libraries you're referring to there's also that much of upkeep that you need to do.
so it's a very delicate balance you want to hit the road running but maintenance and of your third parties is also important.
which i think sometimes when we are writing software we're only thinking about the kind of code we are writing.
but not about all of our third-party libraries that come to this afterthought.
and from what you're saying and what we're seeing in the news as well i think that maybe has to change.
totally agreeable because if your third-party libraries you don't know your ecosystem well you would be in trouble.
for example you have four doors in your house and four windows.
when you go out for a vacation or even to go to the market you close all your doors.
but then you forget to close your windows and there's a thief who comes in takes out everything and goes away.
how would you figure out who will you bring for when you don't know your own house how will you secure it.
correct so that's how the outdated libraries comes into picture or using components with known vulnerabilities.
people emphasizing on the right kind of cmdb or software below materials.
or even getting the right set of actions at the right time where you can track the things right.
yeah sometimes i also wonder you know because if you say like you know npm live libraries.
or we just do this npm install very it's easy right we just do that.
and then i wonder if those kind of things are we thinking about it.
when should we be thinking about what are the libraries that we're going to use at the design stage.
so maybe we could you know try to reduce this kind of dependence on unnecessary libraries.
but i know i don't know if that's an overkill.
maybe this is only things which we'll know when we actually start developing.
and maybe that much is not known at design time or like i don't know what do you think.
i mean do you think we should be doing design like more frequently and not just like as one big bang exercise.
actually it's very subjective because when you talk about libraries it is important you document it properly.
and they're not just from the get go because what happens is like a developer is working on some piece of code.
the person installs something and then leaves the organization.
how would the other person get to know that this is the version that it is installed.
and i'll go back again to the recent incident which happened with springshell the same thing happened.
now how would you handle that how would you take care of all of these things.
it is very very subjective and if a person leaves the organization how would you figure out who did what.
and that's what documentation helps and no doubt design is something which is needed at any given point of time.
so let's document everything right.
maybe that should also be in the oh hospital and yeah right.
i think there was a show on the book on the missing read me for repos thing that's super important.
of course you have your library information in your packages list or whatever.
but i think sort of having a good read me with this document on why you did that as well as you know confluence pages are all very important.
and also i find that sometimes when i just take the effort to read the readmes or the conference pages uh.
i seem to know a lot more than just spending time asking people.
so i think you're documenting like you say is rightly important and reading that as well.
right i agree with you on that.
okay now seventh on the list we've gone through all of this and we're back now to identity and authentication failures.
why is this still on the list i thought we have standardized frameworks now.
and we have all of us are you know using one of the other standardized frameworks to do identity.
but we it still seems to be on the list why do you think that's the case.
because when we are designing we're not designing right that's one of the things for sure.
because we keep deploying like we're not deploying multi-factor authentication.
there was a research which was done in 2017 and if we do the same research now this was done with node.js ecosystem.
what happened is like they figured out that a huge set of people were still using insecure passwords.
and if i speak to you you would say that i'm using my husband's name or some other close person password as my password.
or i use the same password like everywhere again.
quota breach which is uh with a colonial pipeline attack that was again a big one.
what happened someone at the org they had their password used somewhere which was leaked.
and then they interpreted this person might might be somewhere and then they picked up the vpn's credentials.
and and that's how the whole thing pivoted.
now if we would have used a strong password and not the same password repeated at a lot of places or multi-factor authentication that would have been used.
i think it these things could have been avoided.
could have been avoided or there are orgs which are still using the same session identifiers.
why do we even do that let's invalidate the session properly.
why do we have to play around with the session ids.
we have started using single sign-ons we've started using a lot more things but again we're still living in the same era.
and now we are not we're trying to avoid brute force but then there are new ways which are coming up.
it is not like that we're not doing it we're doing it but then it needs more effort more time and more energy synergy.
and like you say even though we have the frameworks the weak link could also be the social engineering.
perfectly said yes absolutely.
you know me you're a good friend of mine but again we are in security you might try.
and i'll tell you a funny thing i shouldn't be saying that.
but a lot of people ping me on linkedin or connect with me and they say we stalk you.
and i'm like you don't stalk me you just try and understand what i do.
but they specifically say that words talking and everyone everyone does that.
and everyone does social engineering or do the open source intelligence whatever lying over there trying to figure out that thing.
and i think those things are very easily you can detect like priyanka if i'm speaking with you you know me for like few years now.
i can say that now you know about my son's name about my family about the likes and dislikes.
when you know that much you can try and guess my passwords probably.
so probably i would say that's not good or you which company i work for.
you try and get my username and from the username you try and brute force it.
is that good no so that's how it leads to a total different position.
i think it's very interesting what you're saying and i just when you're talking about this.
i also remember that last week there was the octa hack that happened.
but of course but i think here again it was a mix of i think not having the right privileges.
which is like yeah of course our number one item on the wasp list.
but also i hear and i have not done enough research on this one.
maybe you know i hear that the third party organization that was hacked maybe somebody sold their credentials.
and that's how they got these actors is that something you are aware of.
i mean i don't know if you've read about i have read about the october breach but i would refrain from commenting on that i'll be very honest. okay okay okay make sense.
but i think one of the things is that i think two things that which would come from any of these.
is that you can have any kind of weak vector.
so one could be just even if the weak vector is somebody you know getting your credentials.
then other thing that needs to be strong is that you have a second gate that kicks in right.
so at least your privileges are okay right.
let's move on to the number eight which is software and data integrity failures.
which actually focuses mainly on trusting software updates without checking for the integrity.
how important is this and do you have any takeaways for our listeners.
absolutely i'll tell you something interesting around it or maybe it's very interesting for me again it ties back to the vulnerable components.
and think of it as we trust certain things so much that we keep updating.
for example open source 80 to 90 percent of the code as per one of the research by sneak itself.
that 80 to 90 of the code on the internet is all open source.
now that's a huge code and only 10 to 20 has been written by the organization.
which means we are so much dependent that if something comes up oh let's update it let's do this.
there's a new update that has come in on this software keep a time off for it because we use it rigorously.
and what happens is this year in january what happened there are two famous frameworks of node.js called caller and faker.
now they both have the same person who's contributing to it who's the leader who's the person behind them.
this person removed the content from the repository for faker and for caller this person added a loop condition.
so anyone who runs this package uh like updates it and then runs the package their system would go in the loop condition.
or would have a sort of a buffer overflow where you your systems would stop working.
so think of it as a very critical situation and there are tons of downloads every week house crazy that would be.
that's why people say that there's there has to be a review process before a change is committed.
and it's not just the only incident there was an incident which happened a few years back with event stream.
which isn't used for over 10 years more than 10 years and suddenly somebody comes and says that i want to help the project leaders start taking help.
and that this person adds a malicious dependency to it wherein any system who ha who is using this particular project will have a crypto miner installed in their system.
now the crypto miner is mining and your system resources are being used isn't that crazy.
that's why when we are setting up the cicd pipeline when we are setting up the whole ecosystem.
let's have these documentation proper signatures proper and we need to have s-bomb which is software bill of materials where we are tracking all of these things.
any tips for like how do you update a third-party component.
so should we be looking at say whether it's properly peer reviewed does it have like number of stars.
like if it's got a five star and this version is good or something like reviews.
i mean what should we be looking at or do we wait a certain period of time in your experience.
i would say it is more important to test it in your lower environment first.
okay and then move it because even if the peer review is done sometimes we tend to miss it it is very humanly right.
so it's best that we test it out in the local system or a dev environment or a system which is not connected to the production.
and then go ahead and start playing around with it or post it to the production.
that's a very good point i think yeah so just don't blindly trust test it out and then yeah start using.
the next content which i think most of the times we don't seem to be doing that.
because either we're pressed for time or it's easier just to update down.
let's move on to the last but one which is the ninth item which is insufficient logging and monitoring.
it's moved up from 10 to nine and as per the industry survey it was also actually ranked number three.
so can you explain why logging and monitoring is important.
and maybe i don't know if you could share maybe examples without naming companies uh where insufficient monitoring actually failed to detect a breach.
again i'll quote equifax for it.
okay okay because sometimes when you have everything right but then the monitoring is not done properly then there are issues.
because most of the companies are using security right it's not new for organizations.
but still the organizations are getting reached because we tend to miss out on certain aspects of logging and monitoring.
so it is like tracking or backtracking something which has already been done.
so if you don't have the logs how would you even do anything with that how would you detect what has happened.
it is not at all advisable to not retain the logs.
you should retain the logs for a certain time or certain period.
and that's why these lock kicks in into picture or these compliances kicks in in in the picture.
super interesting that you're saying and yeah actually without it's difficult to do any sort of investigation without the logging.
and i think that's becoming increasingly difficult also in the microservices world if you don't do it right.
right absolutely we are living in the era where things are going super super fast.
so how would you even detect it how would you even figure out that there are bugs.
yeah which component.
yeah yeah like i can't do it that and even humanly it's not possible.
and we want things to go live on the like lightning speed.
earlier what used to happen when we were working with development teams there is a release after three months six months nine months or even a one year.
now when that happens after the release there's a big party.
now think of is it humanly possible now or is it practically not humanly but practically possible now.
you want everything tomorrow what today how would you do that it is not possible things will fall apart.
yeah i will probably come back to that at the last part of the podcast on the culture aspect but let's move on to the last item.
which is the server side request forgery which you talked about also with the broken access control.
can you explain server side request forgery to our listeners who are sort of not security experts.
because apparently even in the survey it seems to say that security professionals viewed this as more of a threat than say developers.
i would say server side request forgery is nothing but when you are able to fetch data from the server.
and in a way that you can extract the information.
you can instruct the organization or the url to be very precise the url to send some data to somewhere.
for example if you have sql injection and it's a blind sql injection you wouldn't get to know that yes there is an injection or there's some data.
but if you say send the data to this url and then the data is being sent that means there's something which is happening in the background.
similarly the server-side request for study it happens out of band wherein you try and fetch the data which you're not supposed to have access to.
so the access control again plays a very big role.
but i'm an external person and i'm able to scan all your ports all the all the servers which are there and as part of your organization.
and if i have to code a breach and i'll tell you it's a big disclaimer.
that all the breaches that i'm talking about it's there on the internet you can read through it.
and similarly this happened with capital one it was a big credit card bridge.
where a person tried to upload the credit card image and then they figured out that the data is being hosted on a aws s3 bucket.
they started fetching metadata to im credentials to getting the access and ssh keys to those accounts.
and i wouldn't blame anyone but not getting the access right.
and that's how they were able to perform server side request forgery.
and when a breach happens or when there is a vulnerability it does not happen when i would say that it's just a breach or it's just one vulnerability.
it happens in tandem it happens it's in chain if i have to put it like one leads to other other vulnerability leads to the other one.
so you're saying that like it could just not be that one vulnerability it could lead to like many more things.
if it's not you know designed right in terms of access control there could be a lot of other things that you can pick up from there.
that's interesting and scary.
but i think it's great because we've sort of gone through the top 10 for our listeners.
and i'll definitely add the top 10 list again on the show notes.
i'd like to use the last section of the podcast to ask you a few things.
one than i think the the first thing i wanted to ask you was also in terms of the culture.
which we briefly touched upon in the ninth item which is we want things faster.
so i wanted to tie it in with the wasp top 10.
was this guidance to developers that the os top 10 provides.
was it also to kind of influence the software community towards a better culture in terms of software development and life cycle.
and you know going too fast or slow down a bit what's your take on that.
i would say when we talk about security it's everyone's responsibility not mine not yours not developers not security people but everyone in the organization.
so it is important to understand each and educate the people.
developers are supposed to make the application look beautiful the way it should be developed.
but what happens next we start forcing security on them it is not easy.
i have a mindset i have a way of working since inception and now you say oh i had security do it.
and then we start beating them up for it it's not right.
being a security person i can say that now when that's not right let's work to go towards educating.
and education is something which is must and let's have it right i would say.
and that's where it plays a big big role.
education right that's what you say education and yeah peer education is very important.
okay and you know sort of building up on that.
so does wasp work with say tool vendors to help the community catch these flaws.
in terms of like educative tools that does it come from the tool vendors or the community.
that because you have so many of these projects that they're right right how does that work.
does uh is it just the entire community that contributes to that or do you have specific like sponsors who you work with.
i would say that when we talk about oas owasp has so many projects in itself.
so the projects when you look at them they themselves update or educate people.
you can look at any project and at the same time there are conferences which oas post.
and also when owasp hosts these conferences they connect people they have local chapters and these project leaders in turn educate each other.
okay but do you also work with like two vendors or doctors.
yeah not particularly because wasp is vendor neutral community right.
sounds good. i was wondering if you could also tell us a little bit about you know some example open source tools.
that you think that listeners should look at after the show from wasp.
yeah i love all of those projects but i have to tell you web testing id is the place to start off.
if you want to make notes of the use cases ovasp application security verification standard which is called asvs is the place to go.
another important aspect is that if you want to go more deep into it then ovas top 10.
and then there are many many projects for tools for documentation everything is there but you can check it out.
and if you want to know the highlights of it on my youtube channel just look for vandara verma.
i have created a series just for the project which is called oas project spotlight series.
so i reached out to those leaders the project leaders and had a brief chat and the demo of how these tool works how the documentation project works. if that might help.
yeah i can now definitely link to that because i think the oauth spotlight series uh you rightly said.
i i remember catching the one on wasp zap that you've done it was great with simon bennett that was very good.
and i i think also this there's something about the oas juice shop i don't know if it's a part of this thing.
but i remember seeing an introductory thing from that as well from you right.
i think i'm going to add all of that in the show notes sure.
and then how can we as members of the open source community contribute to wasp how does that work.
you can be a project leader you can be a chapter leader.
or if you really want to contribute to a project in detail just go to that project there's a github account.
you can help in refining the language you can help in adding some content to it.
you can help in suggesting that this could also be in there from your experience.
so it really really helps if you help that way or this something that you want to create of your own.
so you can be a project leader there you can submit a project and can be a project leader.
if you want to connect with the community then please join the chapter and if there is no chapter near you please consider starting a new one.
and i guess get in touch with the os board.
oh yes so that's funny yeah absolutely.
okay also in terms of the os top 10 right the survey.
is there a way that the open i mean can how does one contribute to that survey.
do you get invited or is that again is there an announcement that goes out and people can contribute data to that.
i would suggest reaching out to andrew wender stock he's one of the chapter leaders or i would say project leaders for it. and it can be helpful.
this has been great and before i end the show are there any other words of wisdom or advice.
that you'd give us software engineers on what we should be doing right.
apart from looking at the us top 10 and worse without all any other nuggets that we should like look at.
i would say always keep exploring new things.
another important aspect is that there will be vulnerabilities and what you can do is you can educate yourself.
nobody is going to be there for you when the things will start bursting.
so we let's start educating ourselves.
there are so many wonderful re researchers which are out there but we don't look at that.
we have so many wonderful content out there let's take help from it.
brilliant i think yeah that's great so education is the key.
and thank you for coming on this show vandana.
and before i let you go i just want to know where is the best place that people can reach you.
would it be on twitter or linkedin.
yeah you can reach me out on linkedin and twitter both of the places i'm super active.
the handle is with infosec right.
yes absolutely even my website is infosec.com so you can feel free to reach me there.
i will definitely add that to the show notes.
this is priyanka raghavan for software engineering radio thank you for listening.
thank you.
thanks for listening to sc radio an educational program brought to you by ieee software magazine.
for more about the podcast including other episodes visit our website at se radio.net.
to provide feedback you can comment on each episode on the website or reach us on linkedin facebook twitter or through our slack channel at scradio.slack.com.
you can also email us at team sc-radio.net.
this and all other episodes of sc radio is licensed under creative commons license 2.5.
thanks for listening.